Guide to the Herbert F. Janick Jr. Papers MS 012
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series 3: Subject Files, 38885
  - Oral Histories - Student Work - Introduction to Historical Research, 38894
    - Western Connecticut State University -- History., 38895
      - Dr. Richard Asselta (interview) Creator: Asselta, Dr. Richard Interviewer(s): Gary Havican and Vincent VanVorHees Interview location: unknown Running time: 43 min., May 12, 1992; 38955; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 10, Item 5)
        Coverage: 1963-1992
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background; graduated from high school in Stamford, CT; went to UConn for a year; transferred to WestConn because UConn was just too big; graduated from Western w/ bachelor's in secondary education in 1967; Dr. Haas; lived on same block as her; if she saw him not in school, she would ask him why he wasn't; Dr. Ed Rosenberg; Dr. Truman Warner; Peace Corps; did training in San Francisco during "Flower Children Rebellion"; spent time in Vietnam and Marshall Islands; received letter from President Kennedy; good rapport w/ people of the islands; Back in America; it was a culture shock when he first came back; taught at Broadview junior high school; got Master's in anthropology from Western; Race relations in Danbury; Doctorate; from NYU in secondary education and cultural anthropology; Race relations at Western; ACE (Alternative Center for Education); has done it from 1975 until present (1992); Hostility on campus; intimacy on campus; racial tension; Sociology adjunct; "Man and Nature"; New courses
      - Dr. Gertrude Braun (interview) Creator: Braun, Dr. Gertrude Interviewer(s): Ed Miller and Don DeGuzman Interview location: Midtown Campus Running time: 55 min., Apr 27, 1992; 38954; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 10, Item 7)
        Coverage: 1945-1982
        Topics discussed: (side A): "Nature of Man"; there is value in having elective core requirements; it was fixed and everybody had to go through it; faculty had to focus on it; wasn't structure on a specific course; Western couldn't do such a program now (too big and spread out); WestConn's core curriculum; typical of most colleges; usually stayed conservatively in middle of road in requirements; it's been one of its strengths; move away would be devastating; Programs that should return to WestConn; didn't lose many things other colleges lost; less of the "cafeteria" approach to the liberal arts; budget reasons may bring it back; Budgetary problems; the future of Western speaks of the "plush" past; heavy cost of faculty and loss of clerical and maintenance; letting people go and cutting of jobs; faculty not fired yet, but many lost to retirement; Curricular Committee; Music program; around 1945, State Teacher's Colleges were under the State Board of Education; decided each school needed a specialized program; DSTC got teacher preparation in music; Dr. Haas made request for the program; New Haven got physical education and art; Agenda of Curriculum Committee; she began as chairman of committee in 1950s; all committee members appointed in the beginning; Popularity of the Curriculum Committee; everyone wanted to be on the committee; "Nature of Man" came out of the committee; "like one large faculty meeting"; Change in the committee; elections to the committee instead of appointment; different schools/programs being added to committee; she had veto power as chairman, not sure if chair still holds that power; Growth of Western (1960s); transition from teacher's college to state college; the spread of various types of majors (liberal arts, nursing, etc.); moved from music ed to offering bachelor in music degree; University of Bridgeport; making same move as Western at same time, but had problems; Growth of the CSU system; Central had preeminence; up until 1938, Central was only school offering bachelor's degree; Western, Southern, and Eastern were gradually accepted; she was a graduate of New Haven (SCSU); as a student knew all four presidents of the 4 schools; Normal School history; CT followed Massachusetts; Central was the first of the schools; schools were small at first; Evolution of the schools; from Normal Schools to State Teacher's Schools to State Colleges then to State Universities; WestConn compared to the other CSU schools; each has their own identity; Eastern lives in shadow of the university (UConn); Western lives in shadow of private education belief; Central and Southern have bulk of population to attract students; sports gave both name recognition; University name; name given to each by the state; only way to separate the 4 is by act of state legislation; Competitiveness of the colleges; any desire to compete w/ UConn would be from Central; depends on personality of the president (knows presidents at Western and Southern); Dr. Jorgensen; transferred UConn from a agricultural school into the university it became; Presidents of WestConn; current search for a new president; Dr. Feldman; not charismatic; Dr. Haas; greatly respected and loved by everybody; first woman president of a state college in the country; not charismatic, but had ability to move crowds; the college was her life; Buildings of campus; Old Main was first w/ Fairfield Hall following; Higgins Hall came in three phases; Berkshire, followed by addition to Fairfield and Higgins; Memorial Hall came, followed by Litchfield; Library followed by Newbury; Library; was on 2nd and 3rd floor of Old Main when she got to WestConn; she had hoped that it could be preserved and used later because of the beautiful woodwork; White Hall; the purchase was a mistake; had they not purchased it, college would have moved to Westside; would have sold the campus; Westside; land purchased after the purchase of White Hall; plan on buying White Hall would be to buy land in midtown area; when land was purchased, intent was to move entire campus there (side B): State Commission on Higher Education; made to keep the midtown campus alive; move to maintaining split campus; Roberts Ave School; owned and built by city, run by WestConn as a lab school; WestConn will probably eventually purchase the school; it opened in 1954; Westside classroom building; opened in January 1982; she organized the opening of it and moving of faculty into it; intended to be used for another purpose (observational science); not suppose to be first building, suppose to be second building; not sure how decision made to make that the building that got built; Public Works Dept. in Hartford made most of the final decisions; Programs and departments of Westside; business, education, and computer science of math department
      - Dr. Gertrude Braun (interview) Creator: Braun, Dr. Gertrude Interviewer(s): Libbi Intemann and Jen Manna Interview location: Braun's home Running time: 63 min., Apr 16, 1991; 38953; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 10, Item 8)
        Coverage: 194-1991
        Topics discussed: (side A): Career at WestConn; Growth of WestConn; decision to keep campus on White Street was a bad one; they shouldn't have bought Danbury High (White Hall); it impeded the Westside process; Buildings; Higgins first building built after she arrived, followed by Berkshire; the expansion limited space (Student Union, White Hall, Library) delayed building on Westside; Westside; she helped open classroom building in 1982 (year she retired); the building was never named; she was responsible for office assignments and department moves; Competition from other schools; biggest limitation was the dorms space available for students; rents in Danbury were extremely high for poor quality of apartments; roads and public transportation were poor; curriculum also limited interest; Administration; Dr. Haas was very active in pushing curriculum; she was a member CT Council of Higher Ed; Progress; Dr. Haas saw college expanding to offer more than just teacher training; State Board of Education; posed greatest opposition for teacher training schools transition to liberal arts colleges; they wanted them to stay teacher training only; Curriculum; teacher training to liberal arts; later offered business courses; Curriculum Committee; she served as chairman of the group; "Nature of Man"; faculty and administration always interested in the students needs and open to new ideas; still primarily a teacher education school at time program established, which worked in the favor of the program; family atmosphere working together to establish it; the different disciplines contributed to making it; "The Chimney"; the nick name for "Nature of Man"; it was a required course that went through all four years; students opposed it at time, but later saw benefit; when it stopped, split into the various departments; "Monuments of Culture"; preceded "Nature of Man"; just for freshman and sophomore students; the best of this program was instituted into "Nature of Man"; Stagnation of curriculum; the routine of the programs makes them disinteresting; fresh ideas that start off great, ends up less; "Nature of Man" basically became own department from the idea of it being a combination of all the departments; Transfer students; as more came in, they had to make up the missed courses in the "Nature of Man" program, which was difficult; Student screening; moving from first 2 years into the teacher education major; some cases the students were denied the transition; Post; War period; a lot of the changes at the college just happened; Loco Parentis Role; institution taking place of the parent; many were in dorms and the dorms had "house mothers"; it is a "state of mind"; Dr. Haas before president; began as the Dean of Woman and supervisor of the dorm (Fairfield Hall); felt she needed to take care of the girls as if she were their mother; Girls and parents attitudes; many felt as if Dr. Haas was a mother; 1960s; Dr. Haas did what she could to prevent them from coming on campus; Confrontations w/ Dr. Haas; always showed up for confrontations the students wanted to have w/ her; Safety issues; physical safety was a major concern; leaving the dorms and walking around was a risk Dr. Haas was concerned about; many girls wanted no check; in time for dorms, rather have keys; they wanted to come and go as they pleased; 1945; Dr. Haas had been living in dorm as housemother; she was having a house built for her mother; Dr. Jenkins, who was president, died and she became the new president (side B): Dr. Haas and Fairfield Hall; when she left, the rules remained in place; it wasn't until the 1960s that these rules became an issue; Emergency Certification; a program that began in 1949; a lot of people were interested in this program; it came about because of the immediate need for teachers; most of those who got involved were mothers and house wives; took about 3; 4 years to complete; took summer courses and did student teaching during school year; it moved to graduate (MAT); Darien program; expansion of the program; students took course and lab experiments there; search for faculty and evaluation process of the teachers for the program; they were in competition w/ other schools for faculty; eventually had to dismiss them because of the economy; Bad faculty members; it is very difficult to get rid of a bad one because of the process; unions get involved and make it highly difficult; Concluding thoughts; would like to be remembered as being accessible; often agreed to disagree w/ people, she was fair; hated to say no to people
      - Dr. Harold Burke (interview) Creator: Burke, Dr. Harold Interviewer(s): Jenn and Eddy Interview location: unknown Running time: 90 min., ca.Jun 18, 1905; 38952; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 10, Item 9)
        Coverage: 1965-1990s
        Topics discussed: (side A): Beginning at WestConn; came in 1965 from UConn; trained faculty at UConn how to be better teachers and advisors; Role at WestConn; was the first Dean of Student Affairs; dealt w/ 10; 11 departments that worked w/ students; prior to this, all departments worked under Dr. Haas; Newbury Hall; he felt men should have a place to live on campus; while Dr. Haas initially objected, she gave him permission to go ahead; men stayed on 1st and 4th floors and women on floor in between; experiment worked, and later dorms (except Fairfield) became co; ed; Teaching; resigned from position as Dean of Student Affairs in 1976; went into the psychology department to teach; Westside; teachers a summer course there now; original plan was to move everything to that campus; disappointed they couldn't make such a move; the building that was built was not intended to be used for classrooms; Dr. Braun; had the task of informing each department as to whether or not they would be going to Westside or staying; Technological changes; definite improvements; none existed when he first came; first computer was housed near in a brown house near Roberts Ave; primarily used by math department in beginning; expanding business department brought change to computer use; Midtown campus; had college moved to Westside, probably would have been city property; original plan was to expand the midtown campus, like Salem College did; political problems and the hospital stopped those plans; Westside was purchased afterwards; Difference in student body; more men started coming in; impressed w/ graduate level students; influx of NY students because of the business school; Class size; had a class of 80 students; AAUP (teacher's union) got it so classes couldn't exceed 40 (side B): Standard time for classes; basically same M; W; F hours for classes; Tues. and Thurs. class were designed initially for science and labs; Change is staff; Why WestConn; had always wanted to have title of Dean of Student Affairs, so when it was offered to him he took it; Educational Background; undergrad and Master's at Springfield College; Ph D at Boston University; Demonstrations; none at WestConn, but ones at UConn were pretty significant; Jim Dyer; former student and editor of yearbook; later became mayor of Danbury; School name; "Colonials" was voted for, but some wanted "Mudhens"; Alcohol parties; Gale Alexander was in charge; held in downstairs of student union; no hard alcohol or drugs allowed; Rallies; felt he couldn't prevent them, just contain them; they were held in student union
      - Dr. Harold Burke (interview) Creator: Burke, Dr. Harold Interviewer(s): Jim MacDonald and Matt Smith Interview location: unknown Running time: 70 min., May 5, 1992; 38951; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 100 minute] (Box 10, Item 10)
        Coverage: 1965-1992
        Topics discussed: (side A): Positions held; Dean of Student Affairs (1965; 1976); Professor of Psychology (1976; 1984); Adjunct professor in psychology since 1984; Dean of Student Affairs; in charge of departments that dealt w/ students; always had interaction w/ students; believed in students came first; Teaching; enjoys teaching students; Student committees; Change in students; business program didn't exist when he first came; addition added business; minded students; most who came wanted to be teachers; mostly female students; more foreign students began coming in; Foreign students; process of admitting them into college; some difficulties in understanding them because of language; European students came from more heavily book oriented culture; many who worked needed a special work visa to do so and many found they needed to because of exchange rates; some returned after graduating while others stayed; he had a great relationship w/ foreign students; Dr. Haas and relationship w/ students; she had a great relationship w/ students; students came first and established his role of Dean of Student Affairs; Dr. Feldman; business man and was Dean of Business School prior to president role; didn't spend as much time w/ students like Dr. Haas did (nor did Bersi); Type of president for college; need someone who can work well w/ upper level state personnel; business; minded isn't necessarily most important; Vietnam; some reaction was seen on campus, but more milder (mostly women); he came from UConn where reaction was very much seen; reaction wasn't as large or extreme; one time students tried to stop military recruiters from coming in; Racial tensions; complained about being denied equal opportunity; black students had demonstrations about their complaints; he advised hiring someone who could serve as advisor for these students; he suggested that the black students should get a room of their own in the student union (they formed the Afro; American CluB): they made him honorary lifetime member of the club; Gale Alexander; advised him to allow demonstrations to be held in student union; Sensitivity training; part of a national movement; help people to become aware of themselves and about others; did things off campus, had meetings on campus, etc.; always tries to show these things in his classes; Dean to professor; gave up being Dean of Student Affairs in 1976; decided he had enough and wanted to teach; went into psychology department; he kept on doing his work w/ foreign students until his retirement in 1984; Studies skills program; Watergate and Vietnam; some reaction to Nixon's involvement in Watergate; Vietnam War had a more profound impact; Westside; he was heavily involved in planning; initial plans were to move everything over there; budget prevented the move from happening; he visited schools for ideas about designs for the Westside; Courtland was the biggest inspiration for them; he designed 5th floor to the classroom building currently there (it was suppose to be a psychological observation building); Classroom building; they didn't choose that building; state picked it and told them to vote on it; they voted to keep it because they feared voting against it would delay getting any building at all; One campus; not sure if Westside only will ever happen; has taken 20 years to get 3 buildings (side B): His teaching career; taught eleven years at UConn; taught at Springfield College for about seven years; Dean of Student Affairs at WestConn for eleven years and taught full; time for eight years; Diversity of students; more older students coming in; began teaching shortly after WW II, many men returning to college under GI Bill; more women than men at Western (Springfield was opposite) when he first came here; increase in number of students; Dr. Harold Case; was president at Boston University when he was there; considers him the best president he worked for; Commuter school; Dorms; in beginning, no dorms for men; had plan to make Newbury Hall co; ed, but Dr. Haas objected at first; she told him later okay, but it was his responsibility; Fairfield Hall remained only female; Litchfield eventually became co; ed; many foreign students had no place to stay w/ women only dorms in beginning until men allowed in dorms; Foreign students; keeps in touch w/ many former foreign students; many stayed w/ him while they went to WestConn; Rewards of work; students and faculty relationships; started out teaching, then became Dean of Student Affairs before going back into teaching again
      - Dr. John Byrne (interview) Creator: Byrne, Dr. John Interviewer(s): Chuck Ruch and Richard Renza Interview location: Byrne's home Running time: 55 min., ca.Jun 18, 1905; 38950; Number of tapes:2 [tape stock length: 30 minute] (Box 10, Item 11, 12)
        Topics discussed: (tape 1;side A): Background; worked in Washington, DC for defense and intelligence; received Ph D in business from George Washington University; Why WestConn; interviewed by John Riegler; liked area and decided to come; Defense Department; has never talked about his role there; University of Maryland; taught there while he was in DC; also taught within his own agency; Most rewarding university; Maryland was large and G W he spent time working on his degrees; both were impersonal and never realized how so until he came here; Beginning at WestConn; started full; time in fall 1974; only 3 were in business department at time; began part; time January 1974; 1st assignment was to prepare a Master's program; Master's program; his first attempt failed because of politics; UConn felt their MBA program should be only one and convinced state; Dr. Bersi suggested the idea of having an MSA program if they couldn't have the MBA program; the MSA program ran until they were able to get their own MBA program; taught both the undergrad and grad programs in business (tape 1; side B): Experience at WestConn; smaller university; Dr. Haas was like a den; mother to the female students; few protests here; Memorable moments at WestConn; building the programs here; teaching classes at Ethan Allen Inn; Trouble at Maryland; students there protested the tremendous authority faculty had over students, which even included their student government; students protested for more say in student matters; tended to side w/ the students; events at Maryland helped students across country, including WestConn; Quality of Education; business helped school improve because involvement in the departments (tape 2; side A): Dr. Janick; traveled w/ him and his wife to Spain; have historic preservation as a common interest; well known in state for his efforts; has done a lot for Danbury while he has focused on New Milford; Restoration Railway Service; has been helping in getting railway service back to New Milford; has received help from politicians including Nancy Johnson; been a long drawn out process (4; 5 years); feels they are within 3 years of seeing progress; Freetime; historic and railway preservation/restoration; music in Canterbury; exercise; vacations (plans on France); trips to Florida and DC every year; Retirement; found things to be less challenging and less dynamic (tape 2; side B): Bermuda; taught there for about 4 years after he left WestConn in 1986; the program was through the University of Maryland; found students there more motivated than students in U.S.
      - Richard Cyr (interview) Creator: Cyr, Richard Interviewer(s): John Caldwell and Shawn Curioso Interview location: unknown Running time: 62 min., May 8, 1991; 38949; Number of tapes:2 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 10, Item 13, 14)
        Coverage: 1969-1991